Hello, welcome to third day חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, fourth day of
the עומר. Omer. We start today's דף כה. Daf Chaf-Heh. We start
at the bottom of כ"א עמוד ב', Chaf-Aleph Amud-Beis, and we are
in the פרק Perek of דם שחיטה, Dam Shechita, which at least
the first משנה Mishnah is all about which types of things are
included in the איסור Issur of דם, Dam, of blood. The rest
of the פרק, Perek, which we'll get to today, switches topics. But
anyway, bottom of כ"א עמוד ב', Chaf-Aleph Amud-Beis, we had said that
the blood of humans and the blood of fish and grasshoppers is
מותר. Mutar. We mentioned a type of מראית עין, Mar'is Ayin, although
the language was אסור, Assur, the context seemed מראית עין Mar'is Ayin
of fish blood where it's all gathered together, which is in a
cup or something, which is counteracted by if you have the scales
nearby. And then human blood, the language was אסור, Assur, and rabbinically,
what we're trying to figure out is what the degree of אסור
Assur is. There's one case of gathering it up all in a
cup, which really looks like animal blood and so on. And then
there is another case where it's like out of your mouth, but
it's not really all gathered up, and that's the case of דם
על הכיכר, Dam al ha-Kikar, on the bread. And let's take a
look now what the גמרא Gemara says about this. Bottom of כ"א
עמוד ב'. Chaf-Aleph Amud-Beis. אמר רב ששת... Amar Rav Sheshes... this doesn't
work... אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshes, five lines from the bottom,
דם מהלכי שתים, Dam Mehalechei Shtayim, blood of again bipeds, אפילו מצות
פרישה אין בו. afilu mitzvas poresh ein bo. Even a מצות פרישה
mitzvas poresh of like separating yourself from it, there does not apply
to it. Meaning that that's not saying that it's strictly rabbinically forbidden,
but that it's like unseemly, presumably not even מראית עין, Mar'is Ayin,
just because it's like unseemly, you know,
so on its own sort of like aesthetic or religious aesthetic terms,
but not really technically forbidden. That does not apply to human blood.
Don't get all crazy about that. So the גמרא Gemara wants to
figure out, you know, you can drink... well, let's... so the גמרא
Gemara wants to figure out what does he mean. So the גמרא
Gemara says, מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on this, the ברייתא Braisa
we just quoted yesterday: דם הטחול דם הלב דם הכליות דם האיברים,
Dam ha-Tchol, Dam ha-Lev, Dam ha-Klayos, Dam ha-Eivarim, if you have blood
of the spleen, the heart, the kidneys, or of any of the
other organs, הרי אלו בלא תעשה. harei elu be-lo sa'aseh. That's a
negative prohibition, but it's not the soul blood, the life blood. But
it is a negative prohibition. דם מהלכי שתים, Dam Mehalechei Shtayim,
if it is blood of a biped, so דם שרצים ורמשים, Dam
Shratzim ve-Remasim, or the blood of various rodents, אסור ואין חייבים עליו.
assur ve-ein chayavim alav. It's forbidden, but you do not... you're not
חייב. chayav. And again, just to clarify, it does not just mean
you're not חייב כרת, chayav kares, that was the first statement about
the blood of the organs. So here it means that you do
not even transgress a negative prohibition, but it still is אסור assur
at least rabbinically. Now, the blood of the various rodents is forbidden
because as we learned yesterday, that maybe is even biblically forbidden, but
not as blood, it's forbidden because it's part of the rodent. But
here it seems very clear that human blood is at least rabbinically
forbidden. So how could you say there's no problem with human blood?
So the גמרא Gemara says, כי תניא אסור, Ki tanya assur, when
do we say that it's forbidden? Top of כ"ה עמוד א'. Chaf-Heh
Amud-Aleph. דפירש. De-peirash.
When it has separated from the body. כי אמר רב, Ki amar
Rav, when did רב Rav say, or רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, when
did רב ששת Rav Sheshes say that there's absolutely no
problem? דלא פירש. De-lo peirash. It didn't even separate from the body.
No, let's take a look. כי תניא, Ki tanya, like we taught
in a ברייתא, Braisa, דם שעל גבי הכיכר גוררו ואוכלו. Dam she-al
gabei ha-kikar, goreiro ve-ochlo. If you have blood that's on the loaf,
then you have to scrape it off. שבין השיניים, She-bein ha-shinnayim,
if however it's still like your gums are bleeding and it's still
within your mouth and between the teeth,
מוצצו ובולעו ואינו חושש. motzetzo u-vole'o ve-eino choshesh. So we're trying to
say that basically the statement that there's not even a מצות פרישה
mitzvas poresh applies to the case of in between the gums, bleeding
from the gums and still in the teeth and it hasn't even
separated from the body. So therefore nobody sees it, it doesn't look
like blood, maybe it's not even defined yet as blood. So that
is not a problem. Now, the question is of course, so there
are three categories as we discussed yesterday. Hasn't separated at all from
the body, it's like in the gums, in the teeth. It's outside
of the body but it's not gathered together, it doesn't look like
a liquid, or whether it's like on the loaf of bread. And
then there is like you actually pool it all together and put
it into some type of a cup. So before the גמרא's Gemara's
emphasis was to exclude the last case, or to exclude the case
of כנסו kinso when you gathered it together. Here the גמרא Gemara
seems to be saying that anything once it's out of the body
it's automatically אסור assur and that's the case of the כיכר. kikar.
And the question really is again, how do you look at that
כיכר kikar case? Is the כיכר kikar case like an איסור דרבנן,
issur d'rabbanan, sort of like the case of gathered in the cup,
or is that כיכר kikar case just that it's a מצות פרישה,
mitzvas poresh, that's the unseemly, but to really be the technical term
of the ברייתא Braisa of אסור דרבנן, assur d'rabbanan, that requires the
case of when it's really gathered up in the cup. So that's
a little bit unclear from the conclusion of this גמרא. Gemara. Also
relevant to this question is, you know, like I said, what defines
פרישה? poresh? The question about if you have like
a finger that's bleeding, can you like suck it or lick it
or something like that? You know, it's not in the mouth, it's
coming from outside of the mouth into the mouth, but it's still
sort of in the body. So that's an interesting question that some
of the פוסקים Poskim discuss. Yes, sorry, somebody else said...
You said דלא פירש, lo peirash, you mean from you or from
someone else? Like let's say he takes someone's heart and you know,
start like... No, no, no.
From you. Okay. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
Did you do this case today? What? Your finger bleed?
Ah no I told you I wanted you to think about that
as an assignment for the reader. Okay so anyway so now the
גמרא Gemara says like that.
Okay. איכא דמתני לה אהא דרב ששת אהא דתניא. Ika dematni la
aha deRav Sheshet aha detanya.
Some say that the statement about רב ששת Rav Sheshet that it's
מותר mutar and there's not a מצוה mitzvah of פרוש prosh goes
on the following ברייתא braita in כתובות. Ketubot. In the גמרא Gemara
כתובות Ketubot there's a pretty similar סוגיא sugya as our סוגיא. sugya.
דתניא יכול יהא חלב מהלכי שתים יהא אוכלו עובר בלאו. Detanya yachol
yehei chalav mehalechei shtayim yehei ochlo over belav.
Maybe if you eat the milk of humans maybe it is forbidden
because remember there's a הלכה halacha about פורש מן הטמא טמא. poresh
min hatamei tamei.
Right so something that comes from a non-כשר kosher animal is non-כשר.
kosher. So milk from camels or from pigs is not כשר. kosher.
How about milk from humans? Now of course the interesting point is
that humans are not אסור בלאו assur belav meaning the blood of
humans is as we just said not even the blood of humans
is אסור בלאו assur belav that's maybe דרבנן. derabbanan. The meat of
humans when people try to say why would it be אסור assur
to eat humans we discussed before dead humans and so on at
most
they say ושמרתם מאד לנפשתיכם Ushmartem me'od lenafshoteichem or אל תשקצו את
נפשתיכם. Al teshaktzu et nafshoteichem. Do not sort of make yourself disgusting
abominable so that gets but again more of that sort of what's
the word I'm looking for something more than aesthetic. But anyway not
a technical prohibition as much as it's a disgusting type of a
thing to be doing with to your body and with your body.
Anyway so nevertheless although humans are not now it might be an
איסור עשה. issur asei. The איסור עשה issur asei is כל בהמה
טהורה תאכלו. Kol behema tehora tocheilu. So human beings while they're not
a בהמה טמאה behema tmeia they're also not a בהמה טהורה. behema
tehora. Not a בהמה behema so right. So it might be the
איסור עשה issur asei of כל בהמה טהורה תאכלו. Kol behema tehora
tocheilu. So this ברייתא braita assumes that to some degree they are
אסור. assur. Let's assume an איסור עשה issur asei but they're not
really בהמה טמאה. behema tmeia. So what would you say about the
milk of humans? Maybe the milk of humans should be אסור. assur.
So you well okay but babies are not are still not חייב
בחינוך chayav bechinuch but let's say I don't know would you be
able to drink human milk or something? What is the status of
the milk of humans? That is the question. Yes.
This came up recently a chef in Brooklyn took his wife's breast
milk and made cheese.
Oh my gosh did he get in trouble for that?
A lot of people got upset.
I can imagine. Okay so there you go. Okay so assuming that
humans are to some degree אסור assur let's assume an איסור עשה.
issur asei. What is the story about the milk? יכול יהא אוכלו
עובר בלאו. Yachol yehei ochlo over belav. Now again the fact that
it says maybe you're עובר over on a לאו lav is pretty
fascinating since you're not even עובר over on a לאו lav for
humans. But okay. ודין הוא. Vedin hu. And I can make a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
What's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? מה בהמה טמאה שהקלת במגעה החמרת
בחלבה. Ma behema tmeia shehikalt bemaga'ah hichmart bechalavah. A non-כשר kosher בהמה
behema when it dies it's only a נבילה. neveila. That's not as
bad as human as we know a corpse is much more מטמא
metamei than a נבילה. neveila. Nevertheless when it comes to its milk
it is a negative prohibition. מהלכי שתים שהחמרת במגען. Mehalechei shtayim shehichmart
bemaga'an. Bipeds humans when they're dead their corpse creates enormous טומאה. tumah.
אינו דין שתחמיר בחלבן Eino din shetachmir bechalavan or בחלבהן. bechalvahan. Anyway
how much more so should their milk be forbidden and even here
to suggest a לאו. lav. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar the verse teaches
וזה לכם הטמא. Vezeh lachem hatamei. This is for you the טמא.
tamei. This is in the פרשה parsha of non-כשר kosher animals. זה
טמא Zeh tamei only these are טמא tamei these non-כשר kosher animals.
ואין חלב מהלכי שתים טמא אלא טהור Ve'ein chalav mehalechei shtayim tamei
ela tahor and milk of humans is not טמא tamei it's כשר.
kosher. אוציא את החלב שאין שם בכל Otzi et hachalav she'ein sham
bakol maybe I'll exclude milk that does not apply to all. What
does it mean does not apply to all?
That right because the milk of כשר kosher animals is כשר. kosher.
So therefore maybe the milk of humans is כשר. kosher. So maybe
fine although the milk is כשר kosher but sometimes milk is כשר.
kosher. ולא אוציא את הדם Velo otzi et hadam and I won't
exclude the blood of humans ששווה בכל sheshaveh bakol that that is
forbidden from all animals. So maybe blood of humans also whether they're
כשר kosher or non-כשר kosher animals however you conceptualize them maybe their
blood should be אסור. assur. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar וזה לכם הטמא.
Vezeh lachem hatamei. No this is for you the non-כשר. kosher. Again
interestingly that it's again a פסוק pasuk by non-כשר kosher animals. But
nevertheless we're doing the דרשה drasha זה טמא ואין דם מהלכי שתים
טמא אלא טהור. zeh tamei ve'ein dam mehalechei shtayim tamei ela tahor.
This is טמא tamei meaning and there but other things but humans
nothing from humans is טמא. tamei. Again it's a little funny because
that's emphasizing their non-כשר kosher status. Blood is as the ברייתא braita
just says not about the non-כשר kosher status of the animal it's
about blood. But nevertheless the דרשה drasha is these things I'm going
to tell you what's אסור assur and it's only in the animal
world and not human and therefore blood not only milk of humans
is כשר kosher but also the blood of humans technically is כשר.
kosher. So anyway that's a different דרשה drasha than before. Before we
learned it out from a כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'prat u'klal but
either way again we're teaching the principle that blood of humans is
not forbidden. And on this אמר ליה רב ששת Amar lei Rav
Sheshet רב ששת Rav Sheshet said on this אפילו מצות פרוש אין
בו Afilu mitzvat prosh ein bo there's not even a מצוה mitzvah
of cleanliness
or fastidiousness to separate from. from it, there's no problem at all.
Again, here the גמרא Gemara doesn't go on to analyze that and
say, do you mean that if it's even on the bread, do
you mean if it's even gathered? But this is the context in
which he said it, not on our משנה, Mishnah, but on a—but
you know, it says human blood is allowed by this ברייתא braita
that says it from a different דרשה. drasha. And again, the question
is, at what stage is there a problem with human blood about
the issue of פרישה, prisha, what stage is there an actual איסור
דרבנן? issur d'rabbanan?
You're almost suggesting that the human milk would be אסור assur כנוס
בתוך כלי kinnus b'toch k'li then, right? I'm sorry? No, just like,
you know, blood we know, but here they're equating the two and
it seems there's no difference. But we knew before that blood, you
know, if it's separated, then it would be a problem. But no
one would say that, oh, well, now we're equating milk to blood,
that human milk if it's separated would be a problem.
No, no. The גמרא Gemara does in כתובות Ksuvos discuss the question
about a type of a מצות פרישה. mitzvah d'prisha. It is a
good question because where is this מצות פרישה mitzvah d'prisha even coming
from? So I should point out
that the—and that's why is it really like the same as a
מראית עין maris ayin that it looks like blood? So the גמרא
Gemara in כתובות, Ksuvos, for example, discusses the question about a child
after he's weaned to continue to afterwards go back and nurse from
his mother. And the גמרא, Gemara, the phrase there is כאילו יונק
שקץ. k'ilu yonek sheketz. Okay? So there, we're not talking about blood
at all, it's talking about milk, as if someone is suckling either
from a rodent or a rodent. Like somehow the milk after a
child is weaned is also inappropriate for a human to drink breast
milk after weaning. So there also, there it's a similar idea that
clearly it's not like a מראית עין maris ayin concern, right? There
is that sense of פרישה, prisha, some sense of like it's inappropriate,
unseemly, and so on. So that might exist by human breast milk,
and that's a סוגיא sugya in כתובות. Ksuvos. So it is good
that you make that point because again, it points out that we're
not just talking about like מראית עין. maris ayin. There is some
issue of seemliness and appropriateness, yes.
Did we study sometime earlier that human secretions were not pure, some
in some context they're not?
Yes, but that's not טמא. tamei. That's not a question of כשר,
kosher, that's a source of טומאה. tumah. And by the way, interestingly
that you mention that because while I explained the difference here about
animals and humans is that a human מת mes causes more טומאה
tumah than an animal's corpse, רש"י Rashi says that the point is
also that humans can become זבים zavim and נדות niddos and can
become טמא tamei from life and animals cannot.
Does חלב chalav cause טומאה? tumah?
Is חלב chalav one of the—it's a good question, I'm trying to
remember.
Is חלב chalav of a נדה niddah an אב הטומאה av hatumah
or not? I don't remember. There are three categories of
the מעיינות, maayanos, or not מעיינות, maayanos, I don't remember it well.
Okay.
Let's take a look. I remember the top of another דף. daf.
See, now that people learn everything from Bar-Ilan, even if I forget
the דף, daf, because thanks to Bar-Ilan I don't remember דפים dafim
of anything before because I always just search on Bar-Ilan. But at
least I remember where it appears on the גמרא, Gemara, the top
line of another דף. daf.
Yeah,
it is—it's on י"ג ע"ב. yud gimmel amud bais. It's not a
מעיין, maayan, so it's not an אב הטומאה av hatumah like the
spit of a נדה niddah would be or something or a זב
zav or whatever, זבה, zavah, but it is—it is טומאת משקין. tumas
mashkin. It is considered like a liquid, so it's a—it becomes a
ראשון לטומאה. rishon l'tumah. Okay, but it is not one of the
מעיינות, maayanos, it's not one of the heavier
secretions. Okay, but anyway, that's about טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Let's continue
now. Yes?
Is there some implicit assumption here with the classification of humans that
they're part of the animal kingdom as opposed to fish or birds?
You mean maybe that's the phrase of
מהלכי שתים?
mahalchei shtayim? מהלכי שתים, mahalchei shtayim, right.
Ah, that's interesting. All animals, right. That's an interesting point. I mean,
obviously, you know, we would say that as well, but maybe that's
also because the last few days I've been pointing out the funny
phrase מהלכי שתים, mahalchei shtayim, why not just say אדם? Adam? And,
you know, I pointed out that someone speculated that maybe it's some
type of a concern that about, you know, claims of blood libel
and so on, although of course the question is was that at
all relevant when the at the time of the משנה Mishnah and
the ברייתא braita that you didn't want to speak about human blood?
But maybe it's exactly your point, that since the whole point is
to sort of say are they in the animal world or not
and are they being excluded from the animals, so to refer to
them as like a type of a bipedal animal as opposed to
a different category of אדם Adam makes the הוה אמינא hava amina
at least a stronger הוה אמינא. hava amina. So that's interesting. Well,
there are apes.
Well, they more walk on their knuckles.
They walk on their knuckles, yeah.
Kangaroos are מהלכי שתים. mahalchei shtayim. Kangaroos are bipedal. It says מהלכי
שתים, mahalchei shtayim, which means just walks on two. חז"ל Chazal would
not have known about kangaroos.
Okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: תנן התם, tnan hasam, the last of the narrow lines,
הלב קורעו ומוציא את דמו. halev kore'o umotzi es damo. Finally, here's
a משנה Mishnah from חולין Chullin that did talk about, as I
said, חולין Chullin is surprisingly terse about getting rid of the blood
and the fat, but there is this משנה Mishnah that says when
you come to the heart—the heart after שחיטה shechting an animal, you
have to—קורעו, kore'o, tear it, meaning make like a—an incision, lengthwise, widthwise
incision, ומוציא את דמו umotzi es damo and you squeeze out the
blood from obviously, so we're talking here about the walls of the
heart. לא קרעו אינו עובר עליו. lo kera'o eino over alav. If
you did not do that, or maybe it's talking even in the
cavity to get it out of the cavity, you first have to
tear it open to get it out of the cavity.
The גמרא Gemara will actually... . (Wait, I'm looping in
my head, let's just output). *Final check on
"bipeds"*: The speaker says "bipeds" for "tzivim". I will write "bipeds" in
English. *Final check on
"mistasrif"*: The speaker says "mistasrif". The Hebrew is
מסטסריף. mistasrif. *Final check on "dam she'neshamah teluyah bo"*: דם שנשמה תלויה
בו. dam she'neshamah teluyah bo. *Final check on "dam she'neshamah yotzei'ah bah"*:
דם שנשמה יוצאה בה. dam she'neshamah yotzei'ah bah. *Final check on "dam
neshamah"*: דם נשמה. dam neshamah. *Final check on "Rav Zeira"*: רב זירא.
Rav Zeira. *Final check on "Rav"*: רב. Rav. *Final check on "Gemara"*:
גמרא. Gemara. *Final check on "Mishnah"*: משנה. Mishnah. *Final check on "lo
shanu ela belev of"*: לא שנו אלא בלב עוף. lo shanu ela
belev of. *Final check on "de'leika"*: דליכא. de'leika. *Final check on "de'ika"*:
דאיכא. de'ika. *Final check on "assur vechayav alav"*: אסור וחייב עליו. assur
vechayav alav. *Final check on "vechayav kareit"*: וחייב כרת. vechayav kareit. *Final
check on "dam hatichol dam halev dam haklayot"*: דם הטחול דם הלב
דם הכליות. dam hatichol dam halev dam haklayot. *Final check on "harei
eilu belo ta'aseh"*: הרי אלו בלא תעשה. harei eilu belo ta'aseh. *Final
check on "assur ve'ein chayavin alav"*: אסור ואין חייבין עליו. assur ve'ein
chayavin alav. *Final check on "ki tanni ein chayavin alav al dam
dilei"*: כי תני אין חייבין עליו על דם דיליה. ki tanni ein
chayavin alav al dam dilei. *Final check on "ki ka'amar Rav
de'ati lei mei'alma"*: כי קאמר רב דאתי ליה מעלמא. ki ka'amar Rav
de'ati lei mei'alma. *Final check on "dam dilei hainu dam evarim"*: דם
דיליה היינו דם איברים. dam dilei hainu dam evarim. *Final check on
"uletameich mi lo tanni dam klayot"*: ולטעמיך מי לא תני דם כליות.
uletameich mi lo tanni dam klayot. *Final check on "u'tanni dam evarim"*:
ותני דם איברים. u'tanni dam evarim. *Final check on "tanni vehadar tanni"*:
תני והדר תני. tanni vehadar tanni. *Final check on "hachi nami tanni
vehadar tanni"*: הכי נמי תני והדר תני. hachi nami tanni vehadar tanni.
*Final check on "mei'alma vehaycha ati lei"*: מעלמא והיכא אתי ליה. mei'alma
vehaycha ati lei. *Final check on "besha'ah she'neshamah yotzei'ah"*: בשעה שנשמה יוצאה.
besha'ah she'neshamah yotzei'ah. *Final check on "mistasrif"*: מסטסריף. mistasrif. *Final check on
"dam she'neshamah yotzei'ah bah"*: דם שנשמה יוצאה בה. dam she'neshamah yotzei'ah bah.
*Final check on "dam neshamah"*: דם נשמה. dam neshamah. *Final check on
"dam she'neshamah teluyah bo"*: דם שנשמה תלויה בו. dam she'neshamah teluyah bo.
*Final check on "shechitah"*: שחיטה. shechitah. *Final check on "lo ta'aseh"*: לא
תעשה. lo ta'aseh. *Final check on "kareit"*: כרת. kareit. *Final check on
"kezayit"*: כזית. kezayit. *Final check on "of"*: עוף. of. *Final check on
"beheimah"*: בהמה. beheimah. *Final check on "meitivei"*: מיתיבי. meitivei. *Final check on
"tichol"*: טחול. tichol. *Final check on "klayot"*: כליות. klayot. *Final check on
"mei'alma"*: מעלמא. mei'alma. *Final check on "uletameich"*: ולטעמיך. uletameich. *Final check on
"tanni vehadar tanni"*: תני והדר תני. tanni vehadar tanni. *Final check on
"besha'ah she'neshamah yotzei'ah"*: בשעה שנשמה יוצאה. besha'ah she'neshamah yotzei'ah. *Final check on
"dam she'neshamah teluyah bo"*: דם שנשמה תלויה בו. dam she'neshamah teluyah bo.
*Final check on "shechitah"*: שחיטה. shechitah. *Final check on "dam she'neshamah yotzei'ah
bah"*: דם שנשמה יוצאה בה. dam she'neshamah yotzei'ah bah. *Final check on
"dam neshamah"*: דם נשמה. dam neshamah. *Final check on "Rav Zeira"*: רב
זירא. Rav Zeira. *Final check on "Rav"*: רב. Rav. *Final check on
"Gemara"*: גמרא. Gemara. *Final check on "Mishnah"*: משנה. Mishnah. *Final check on
"lo shanu ela belev of"*: לא שנו אלא בלב עוף. lo shanu
ela belev of. *Final check on "de'leika"*: דליכא. de'leika. *Final check on
"de'ika"*: דאיכא. de'ika. *Final check on "assur vechayav alav"*: אסור וחייב עליו.
assur vechayav alav. *Final check on "vechayav kareit"*: וחייב כרת. vechayav kareit.
*Final check on "dam hatichol dam halev dam haklayot"*: דם הטחול דם
הלב דם הכליות. dam hatichol dam halev dam haklayot. *Final check on
"harei eilu belo ta'aseh"*: הרי אלו בלא תעשה. harei eilu belo ta'aseh.
*Final check on "assur ve'ein chayavin alav"*: אסור ואין חייבין עליו. assur
ve'ein chayavin alav. *Final check on "ki tanni ein chayavin alav al
dam dilei"*: כי תני אין חייבין עליו על דם דיליה. ki tanni
ein chayavin alav al dam dilei. *Final check on "ki ka'amar Rav
de'ati lei mei'alma"*: כי קאמר רב דאתי ליה מעלמא. ki ka'amar Rav
de'ati lei mei'alma. *Final check on "dam dilei hainu dam evarim"*: דם
דיליה היינו דם איברים. dam dilei hainu dam evarim. *Final check on
"uletameich mi lo tanni dam klayot"*: ולטעמיך מי לא תני דם כליות.
uletameich mi lo tanni dam klayot. *Final check on "u'tanni dam evarim"*:
ותני דם איברים. u'tanni dam evarim. *Final check on "tanni vehadar tanni"*:
תני והדר תני. tanni vehadar tanni. *Final check on "hachi nami tanni
vehadar tanni"*: הכי נמי תני והדר תני. hachi nami tanni vehadar tanni.
*Final check on "mei'alma vehaycha ati lei"*: מעלמא והיכא אתי ליה. mei'alma
vehaycha ati lei. *Final check on "besha'ah she'neshamah yotzei'ah"*: בשעה שנשמה יוצאה.
besha'ah she'neshamah yotzei'ah. *Final check on "mistasrif"*: מסטסריף. *Final check on "dam
she'neshamah yotzei'ah bah"*: דם שנשמה יוצאה בה. dam she'neshamah yotzei'ah bah. *Final
check on "dam neshamah"*: דם נשמה. dam neshamah. *Final check on "dam
she'neshamah teluyah bo"*: דם שנשמה תלויה בו. *Final check on "shechitah"*: שחיטה.
shechitah. *Final check on "lo ta'aseh"*: לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. *Final check
on "kareit"*: כרת. kareit. *Final check on "kezayit"*: כזית. kezayit. *Final check
on "of"*: עוף. of. *Final check on
"beheimah"*: בהמה. beheimah. *Final check on "meitivei"*: מיתיבי. meitivei. *Final check on
"tichol"*: טחול. tichol. *Final check on "klayot"*: כליות. klayot. that some po-
you know, by the way, the whole issue about brain death is
a moot point if, you know, and I actually have felt that
it was a strategic mistake for the proponents of the brain death
sort of definition to try to say, oh, there's a there's a
definition, a הלכתית halakhic definition of death called brain death. Because really,
you
it's the same it's the same practical point if you basically say
that death is defined by non-spontaneous respiration, you just don't wait for
cessation of of what do you call it, of of of the
blood, what's the word I'm looking for here? Yeah, there's a word.
Charlie, help me here, technical diff- no, no, no, anyway, cardiovascular whatever.
Anyway, whatever, fine. Anyway, because so what because the whole issue, for
example, about organ donation, I'm digressing here for a minute, but anyway,
the whole issue for organ donation is because after the blood when
the system is shutting down, you know, after the after the first
thing that stops is the lungs. But the heart has an internal
pacemaker, and therefore the heart will continue beating on itself even after,
you know, even after the lungs aren't beating and and so on,
and therefore if you wait for the heartbeat to stop, then the
other organs are deprived of oxygen and can't be used for organ
donation, where if you just waited for the for the you know
for the cessation of breathing, you could still organ donation would still
be feasible. Charlie will correct me here if I'm incorrect, but I
don't think I am. So anyway, so so therefore and the real
problem so the real question is not is not brain death versus
versus
versus using breathing, the real issue is is whether it's breathing and
circulation or just breathing. And all of the גמרות Gemaras talk about
breathing. They don't talk about circulation. One minute. There's one or two
later אחרונים Achronim that mention circulation and it's a question whether they
really mean that, some of them clearly mean breathing. Anyway, some people
point to a רש"י Rashi too that mentions that mentions the heart
when the גמרא Gemara talks about checking, you know, the nose and
whatever, but nevertheless, the point is of all of this is is
that according the גמרא Gemara and רש"י Rashi and all the way
through the חכם צבי Chacham Tzvi who talked about circulation did not
think that the heart was an organ of circulation. They actually thought
that the heart was this goes way back to the ancients was
an organ of transferring the breath throughout the body. And they speak
about the heart being the place not of just נשמה neshama but
נשימה neshima and the breathing. They actually thought that the that what
happens is the breath comes in through the lungs, goes to the
heart to get warmed up, and then from the heart it goes
throughout the rest of the body. So the real point is anyway,
so this is parenthetical that whatever anybody until the last 50 years
mentioned the heart, they were talking about it as a type of
a breathing apparatus and the real הלכתית halakhic definition of death is
breathing and it makes the whole brain death controversy moot. Okay, but
that's another discussion. Anyway, back to here, the גמרא's Gemara question is
where did the blood get Now you understand the question of where
did the heart get blood? Because it didn't seem that there was
blood in the heart, believe it or not, actually thought, which makes
you really wonder because anytime you open up a heart you see
blood, but here you have an explanation, how does that blood get
there? Okay, and the blood got there because and now you understand
the phrase משעת הנשמה יוצאה, mishas haneshama yotza, because if נשמה's neshama
connected to נשימה, neshima, so it means when the breath is leaving
the heart, when the animal dies, so the breath that's in the
heart leaves the heart, then it creates a vacuum and blood is
able to come into the heart. So actually that seems to really
be what the גמרא Gemara is discussing is not how do you
know life blood is in the heart, but how do you know
any blood how did any blood get into the heart? And that
has to do with your assumption that the heart is a organ
of breathing according to the גמרא, Gemara, not an organ of circulation
of blood. Did you want to say something, Charlie?
Oh, nobody, no non-Jew knew about blood circulation until about 400 years
ago.
Right, Harvey, right? William Harvey. Right, and some people try to make
a point that the חכם צבי Chacham Tzvi that wrote this whole
תשובה teshuvah about the importance of the heart, it was a whole
case about a chicken that was believed to not have had a
heart, came at the time of Harvey and maybe he was drawing
on Harvey. The funny thing is is that if you read the
חכם צבי Chacham Tzvi closely, he talks about the heart is so
important because it circulates the breath. And it's all about the breath.
So it's anyway, okay, another conversation. All right, I digress. Yes, moving
on.
דם שאינו יוצא מעצמו
Dam
she-eino
yotzei me-atzmo is okay.
Yeah, if it's דם איברים שלא פירש. dam eivarim shelo peirash. Right,
that the גמרא Gemara isn't discussing, that is the that is true,
that's another סוגיא. sugya. Okay, which is why you can by the
way roast meat and you don't have to salt it, because any
blood that's left in the איברים eivarim that's סתם שלא פירש stam
shelo peirash is actually מותר. muttar. The whole reason you can't do
that for cooking is when you cook the meat, the blood comes
out and goes back in.
But if you're talking about blood in the heart
in the walls It means after if you separated it from the
walls of the heart, it would be לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. But
while it remains within the walls of the heart, it's not a
problem.
You shouldn't squeeze it.
You shouldn't squeeze it out, that's absolutely correct. Okay, moving on. So
that is the issue about the blood in the cavity of the
heart, that is a problem. Now we go to the last thing,
which is blood that comes through bloodletting, that comes from a vein
and that that also could be דם נשמה. dam neshama. דם שהנשמה
יוצאה בו חייב עליו. Dam she-haneshama yotzei bo chayav alav. Blood that
the soul is dependent on or literally goes out with is you're
חייב. chayav. Now of course when the animal is dying you could
talk about there being blood that the life went out with, but
how about the blood that came out during a bloodletting? letting. There,
the animal didn't die, so it doesn't literally mean that the blood
went out with, so it has to be reinterpreted as that the
soul is dependent on. איתמר: Itmar: איזהו דם הקזה שהנשמה תלויה בו,
eizehu dam akaza she-haneshama teluya bo, and notice here although the שיטה
מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet tries to change the גירסא, girsa, here the גירסא
girsa is what is the blood of bloodletting that the soul is
not goes out with, because the animal didn't die, but the phrase
here is that the soul is dependent on. So it's considered to
be lifeblood and not just other types of blood. So, רבי יוחנן
אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar כל זמן שמקלח, kol zman she-mekale'ach, as long
as it is squirted. Apparently what happens at a bloodletting is first
there's a little dripping, and then it squirts out in a more
sort of powerful force, and then it drips at the end. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said only the blood that's coming out when
it's sort of at the force, when it's squirting out, that's lifeblood,
not the beginning, not the end. וריש לקיש אמר Ve-Resh Lakish amar
מטיפה משחרת ואילך. mi-tipa mashcheret va-eilach. No, from the black drop
onwards. Basically, first a black drop, some black drops come out, then
red drops, then they're squirting, and then presumably it's somewhat of the
parallel, you know, the mirror image at the end, that it starts
dripping and first it drips red and then it drips black. At
least that's what רש"י Rashi says, I haven't tested it. So anyway,
so ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said, no, it's after that initial black
dot onwards, okay, that basically once it starts being the red blood
even if it's not squirting out. So now the גמרא Gemara says
מיתיבי, meitivei, asks on this, איזהו דם
הקזה שהנשמה יוצא בו? eizehu dam akaza she-haneshama yotze bo? We have
a ברייתא. braita. What is the blood of bloodletting that the soul
goes out with or is dependent on? כל זמן שמקלח, Kol zman
she-mekale'ach, as long as it's squirting, יצא דם התמצית yatza dam ha-tamtzit
to exclude blood of, you know, of the squeezing. It's not exactly
clear, you know, what this means, it might mean sort of like,
you know, but anyway, it's דם התמצית dam ha-tamtzit is the opposite
of דם הנשמה. dam ha-neshama. Anyway, מפני שהוא שותת, mipnei she-hu shotet,
because at that stage it's only dripping. So that seems to be
like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, excluding the dripping stages and only having
the squirting stages.
מאי לאו אפילו ראשון ואחרון דשותת, Mai lav afilu rishon ve-acharon de-shotet,
don't we see that even the early blood and the end blood
that's just dripping, that's like this non-lifeblood דמי dami type? תיובתא דריש
לקיש, Tiyuvta de-Resh Lakish, and that's a contradiction to ריש לקיש, Resh
Lakish, it's only the squirting blood that's a problem. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא, lo, למיעוטי דם המשחיר, le-mi'utei dam ha-mashchir, it's excluding
the black blood. אבל דם ראשון ואחרון אף על גב דשותת היינו
דם הנפש, Aval dam rishon ve-acharon af al gav de-shotet hainu dam
ha-nefesh, but the blood in the beginning and the end, if it's
red blood, even though it is dripping, it is still the soul
blood. Again, that's hard to read that into the language of the
ברייתא braita that spoke about squirting as opposed to dripping, but here
he's really saying the real contest is black blood versus the red
blood. מיתיבי, Meitivei, asks on this, איזהו, eizehu, we have another ברייתא,
braita, איזהו דם ראשון eizehu dam rishon or some trick's גירסא girsa
from ראשון rishon to דם הנפש dam ha-nefesh I think.
דם הנפש כל זמן שמקלח, Dam ha-nefesh kol zman she-mekale'ach, as long
as it's squirting, יצא ראשון ואחרון מפני שהוא שותת, yatza rishon ve-acharon
mipnei she-hu shotet, as opposed to beginning and end blood that drips.
Again, this seems very clearly to be רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. תיובתא
דריש לקיש. Tiyuvta de-Resh Lakish. So אמר לך, amar lach, ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish will say to you, תנאי, tannai, alright, I admit, fine,
there are some תנאים, tannaim, but actually there's some תנאים tannaim that
agree with me. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, איזהו
דם הנפש, eizehu dam ha-nefesh, what is the soul blood? כל זמן
שמקלח, Kol zman she-mekale'ach, as long as it's squirting, דברי רבי אלעזר,
divrei Rabbi Elazar, that's what רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says, or some
say דברי רבי. divrei Rabbi. Anyway, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, מטיפה משחרת
ואילך. mi-tipa mashcheret va-eilach. No, after the black drop is done. So
this exact debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish turns out to be a debate of תנאים. tannaim. תנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל, Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael, we taught in the house of
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, ודם חללים ישתה, ve-dam chalalim yishte, they will
drink the blood of corpses. פרט לדם קילוח, Prat le-dam kilu'ach, now
from there we learn that blood, actually this was yesterday's question, I
forgot it was today's דף, daf, that blood from a corpse, blood
from a dead human or a dead animal, can't be, is like
liquid, can be מכשיר, machshir, because it says ישתה, yishte, like you
drink it. So since it's used in that metaphor, blood is a
liquid to be מכשיר machshir to make things susceptible for טומאה. tumah.
So now we are saying which blood, right? That was the question,
which bloods of animals and of humans would be? So here we
say פרט לדם קילוח, prat le-dam kilu'ach, excludes the blood of squirting,
שאינו מכשיר את הזרעים, she-eino machshir et ha-zra'im, which would not be
מכשיר. machshir. Where's it being excluded? So רש"י Rashi says the דרשה
drasha is only the blood of corpses. When it comes to human
blood, it's only blood that comes out after the human is dead
that is considered to be a liquid to be מכשיר. machshir. Blood
that comes out while the human is alive or even dying, the
squirting blood, that would not be.
דם הנפש
Dam ha-nefesh is not מכשיר. machshir. Now תוספות Tosafot points out that
there's גמרות Gemarot by בהמה behema that it sounds the opposite, and
תוספות Tosafot actually says you're right, it is different by בהמה, behema,
because from בהמה behema we learn it from a different פסוק. pasuk.
We learn it from על הארץ תשפכנו כמים, al ha-aretz tishpachenu ka-mayim,
and that it's treated like water, you know, when you שחט shacht
an animal, the פסוק pasuk about על הארץ תשפכנו, al ha-aretz tishpachenu,
and there we actually say that דם הקילוח dam ha-kilu'ach is מכשיר
machshir by בהמה. behema. So it's somewhat of the inverse of human.
Anyway, moving on. Conceptual reason for that?
I don't know.
If there is, I don't know it.
But yes, דם המכשיר dam ha-machshir doesn't mean blood which is black,
but blood which becomes black. So you have blood that when it
coagulates becomes darker, right? Right. Raw, but a drop that falls and
becomes darker much more quickly than a large amount. Hmm.
So that's interesting.
So you're saying just the first little
drops.
I was wondering, why would the initial blood be black? Yeah, I
was wondering about that too. Thank you. I very much like that.
That's good פשט. pshat. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
בעי מיניה רמי בר חמא מרבי זירא הקיז דם לבהמה וקיבל דמה
בשני כוסות מהו. Ba'ei minei Rami bar Chama me-Rabbi Zeira hikkiz dam
le-behemah ve-kibbel damah bi-shnei khosot mahu. So this really, it's a strange,
this question is strange because it seems to just be a way
of reframing what we already said. So let's say you're letting blood
of an animal and you collected the blood in two different vessels,
like one vessel filled up and then you got another one. So
the point being that in the, you know, not both of the
vessels don't have the same state and only certain stages of the
blood we said would actually be considered כרת. kares. So what's the
idea, sorry, if it got filled up two vessels? So he says
like this: על הראשון דברי הכל חייב. Al ha-rishon divrei ha-kol chayav.
On the first one, everybody agrees you're חייב chayav because that had
in it the blood of the squirting. That was in vessel number
one because apparently the blood before the squirting is very little, so
obviously a significant amount is the squirting blood and therefore it's life
blood and you get כרת. kares. על האחרון מי מחייב או לא?
Al ha-acharon mi mechayev o lo? So I know the first one,
everybody agrees. How about the second one? That had primarily maybe the
dripping blood and not the squirting blood. You wonder how you exactly
know to draw the line. Anyway, אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said
to him, פלוגתא דרבי יוחנן וריש לקיש, Pelugta de-Rabbi Yochanan ve-Resh Lakish,
which is fine, we could have expected that. That's their debate. דאיתמר
הקיז דם לבהמה וקיבל דמה בשני כוסות. De-itmar hikkiz dam le-behemah ve-kibbel
damah bi-shnei khosot. You collected it in two different vessels. ריש לקיש
אמר חייב שתי חטאות. Resh Lakish amar chayav shtei chatta'ot. You bring
two חטאות, chatta'ot, presumably you remembered in between so they were different
acts of drinking the blood. So for each vessel you're חייב chayav
a חטאת. chattas. Each one has blood of a כרת. kares. ורבי
יוחנן אמר אינו חייב אלא אחת. Ve-Rabbi Yochanan amar eino chayav ella
achat. Only for the first one because again, presumably in the second
vessel, again I don't know how we know this, depends how big
the vessel is, depends how big the בהמה behemah is, but somehow
in the second vessel we're assuming is not enough, not a שיעור
shi'ur of the squirting blood, there's only the dripping blood that comes
at the end. So it's just an application of the earlier debate.
Okay. So that's the question about the blood that comes from bloodletting.
רבי יהודה מחייב בדם התמצית. Rabbi Yehuda mechayev be-dam ha-tamtzit. Rabbi Yehuda
says you are, you get actually not only כרת kares for non-life,
not only a לאו lav for non-life blood, but even כרת. kares.
That for all blood of animals, you get כרת. kares. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי אלעזר. Amar Rabbi Elazar. Now it might
not include, by the way, the blood that's absorbed in the walls
of the organs. But any blood that comes out of veins, we
don't distinguish between life blood and non-life blood. Not clear how broad
דם התמצית dam ha-tamtzit would go. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar,
מודה רבי יהודה לעניין כפרה. Modeh Rabbi Yehuda le-inyan kapparah. Although he
says that this, that it's all the same, it's all the same
for כרת. kares. But when it comes to blood you can use
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, he agrees conceptually there are two categories. There's
life blood and non-life blood. It's just for כרת kares you get
it for both. But for what you use for the blood on
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, that is only the life blood. But that he
does agree. How do we know that? שנאמר, She-ne'emar, the פסוק pasuk
says, כי הדם הוא בנפש יכפר. Ki ha-dam hu ba-nefesh yekhapper. The
blood is the soul and or through the soul it atones. So
you need blood that is, has this life force in it. דם
שהנפש יוצאה בו מכפר. Dam she-ha-nefesh yotze'ah bo mekhapper. The blood that
the soul departs with, that can be used for
atonement. ושאינו הנפש יוצאה בו אינו מכפר. Ve-she-eino ha-nefesh yotze'ah bo eino
mekhapper. It cannot be used for atonement.
Unless you get them mixed together, is that?
All right, that's a discussion in זבחים Zevachim about דם מבטל דם
dam me-vattel dam and whatever. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, אף אנן נמי תנינא. Af anan nami tanina. We
taught similarly, you can infer that Rabbi Yehuda agrees from this, from
the following ברייתא. braisa. דתניא דם. De-tanya dam. This is a ברייתא
braisa that we're going to say is Rabbi Yehuda, it's a ספרא,
Sifra, it's going like Rabbi Yehuda. And it's from the פסוק pasuk
that says כל דם לא תאכלו, Kol dam lo tokhelu, don't eat
blood. מה תלמוד לומר כל דם? Mah talmud lomar kol dam? Why
didn't it just say דם לא תאכלו? Dam lo tokhelu? Why does
it have to say any blood? לפי שנאמר כי הדם הוא בנפש
יכפר. Lefi she-ne'emar ki ha-dam hu ba-nefesh yekhapper. Since it says that
the soul is in the blood and that's how you achieve atonement,
הייתי אומר אין לי אלא דם קדשים שהנפש יוצאה בו שמכפר. Hayiti
omer ein li ella dam kodashim she-ha-nefesh yotze'ah bo she-mekhapper. Maybe the
only thing you get כרת kares for is blood of sacrifices that
the soul departs, that maybe you need both categories to get כרת,
kares, right? Maybe it has to be sacrificial blood and the one
that the soul departs with, the one that's really going to be
used for atonement. Maybe that's the only thing you get כרת kares
for. דם חולין, Dam chullin, if it is non-sacrificial blood, or דם
תמצית, dam tamtzit, blood that is, does not have the soul depart
with it, just the normal types of blood, מניין? minayin? How do
I know you get כרת kares anyway for that, even if it's
not sacrificial or it's not דם הנפש? dam ha-nefesh? תלמוד לומר כל
דם, Talmud lomar kol dam, any blood. And so what do you
see? You see this ברייתא, braisa, first of all you see where
Rabbi Yehuda gets his idea that it's even if it's not דם
הנפש. dam ha-nefesh. But what you also see is he agrees that
there is a category of דם הנפש dam ha-nefesh that applies to
what you use for the sacrifices, right? And that's why he said
maybe we would limit it to this category, but that category does
exist. תלמוד לומר כל דם. Talmud lomar kol dam. וסתם ספרא מני
רבי יהודה היא. Ve-stam Sifra mani Rabbi Yehuda hi. And that's a
ספרא, Sifra, the commentary on ויקרא Vayikra which we say is Rabbi
Yehuda. And therefore you see that he says very clearly that, that
there's some blood you use for sacrifices, not all blood. But when
it comes to the prohibition of blood for eating and getting כרת,
kares, that's all blood. So that was thrown in in the middle
here, a whole משנה Mishnah discussion about blood. And now we go
back to our regularly scheduled programming of
about questions about how many חטאות chatta'ot and how many אשמות ashamos
can you
bring. So we discussed אשם תלוי, asham talui, we discussed חטאת chatas
and אשם תלוי. asham talui. Now we're discussing what do you bring
an אשם תלוי asham talui for? Certainly you bring an אשם תלוי
asham talui for something you would otherwise bring a חטאת chatas for.
Would you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui for something you would
otherwise bring an אשם asham for? So if you have a doubt
whether you did מעילה, me'ilah, if you definitely did מעילה me'ilah you
bring an אשם. asham. If you have a doubt whether you did
מעילה, me'ilah, would you bring an אשם תלוי? asham talui? So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said yes, וחכמים פוטרין, vachachamim potrin,
and the חכמים chachamim exempt. By the way, an אשם, asham, as
we're going to see in the גמרא, gemara, מעילה me'ilah is different
from a normal, from a normal case in two ways. Number one,
it's a חטאת, chatas, not an אשם. asham. I mean, sorry, it's
an אשם, asham, not a חטאת. chatas. And number two, the normal
thing that you bring the חטאת chatas for and therefore an אשם
תלוי asham talui for is something you would get כרת. kareth. מעילה
me'ilah you don't get כרת. kareth. Might be worse, whatever, you might
be מיתה בידי שמים misah bidei shamayim or something else, but anyway,
but you don't get כרת kareth for. Okay? So it's worse, so
therefore it's different in two ways, and nevertheless רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says you would bring an אשם תלוי asham talui if you don't
know if you did מעילה. me'ilah.
Actually there's a question about which is worse, כרת kareth or מיתה
בידי שמים, misah bidei shamayim, but anyway it's different. ומודה רבי עקיבא
שאינו מביא את מעילתו עד שיתודע לו שיביא עמה אשם ודאי. umodeh
Rabbi Akiva she'eino meivi es me'ilaso ad sheyivada lo sheyavi imah asham
vadai. So מעילתו me'ilaso here means what you, what you basically stole
from הקדש. hekdesh. So you're going to bring an אשם תלוי, asham
talui, but we're not going to say you have to pay back
the money unless it's clear to you that you actually did take
the money, okay, that you did misuse הקדש. hekdesh. All right? So,
and don't think that the atonement or the effect of an אשם
תלוי asham talui is dependent on that. Right? You understand, it's a
fascinating case also, it's another way אשם מעילות asham me'ilos is different.
It's not just, as it were, a sin, it's also a crime.
You took something away from הקדש. hekdesh. So he says you can,
you bring your אשם תלוי asham talui if you don't know, but
you don't yet pay the money because you're not, you're not sure
you're obligated, and you don't need to pay the money to get
the effect of the אשם תלוי. asham talui. When you become aware
that you definitely took from הקדש, hekdesh, if you become aware that
you definitely, then you'll bring your אשם ודאי asham vadai and you'll
pay the money back. Okay. So אמר רבי טרפון, amar Rabbi Tarfon,
so says רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, מה לזה מביא שתי אשמות? mah
lazeh meivi shtei ashamous? So he doesn't in principle disagree with רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but he just says why are you making this
guy, you know, spend, buy two אשמות? ashamos? Meaning he'll buy an
אשם ודאי asham vadai now and an אשם תלוי asham talui now,
and if it turns out he stole, he's going to have to
bring another אשם asham for his אשם ודאי. asham vadai. Well heck,
they're both the same animal, they're both an אשם, asham, let's just
save you the cost of one of the אשמות. ashamos. How are
we going to do that? אלא מביא מעילה וחומשה. ela meivi me'ilah
vechumshah. You bring what you stole or might have stolen and the,
and the fifth, the 20%, actually 25%. So you take the money,
ויביא אשם בשני סלעים, veyavi asham bishnei sela'im, two סלעים, sela'im, because
we're going to find out that the minimum price of an אשם,
asham, whether it's an אשם תלוי asham talui or an אשם מעילה,
asham me'ilah, is two סלעים. sela'im. Okay? So you bring your אשם,
asham, and the reason of emphasizing the money is to say I
don't want you to have to buy two of them, buy one
of them, ויאמר, veyomar, and you stipulate and you say the following:
אם ודאי מעלתי, im vadai ma'alti,
if it turns out that I actually did take from הקדש hekdesh
and I did sin, זו מעילתי וזו אשמי, zu me'ilasi vezu ashami,
here's my money paid back and this is my אשם ודאי, asham
vadai, if it turns out that I actually did sin. ואם ספק
מעלתי, ve'im safek ma'alti, if however I only doubtfully sinned, and of
course the גמרא gemara is going to say what do you mean?
You did doubtfully sin. Okay, but we'll get back to that. If
it somehow turns out that I don't need an אשם ודאי, asham
vadai, then המעות נדבה, hama'os nedavah, the money is a gift, then
I wouldn't have to give the money, ואשם תלוי, ve'asham talui, and
let this be an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Now why are you
able to do that? שמין שהוא מביא על הודע מביא על לא
הודע. shemin shehu meivi al hoda meivi al lo hoda. It's the
same animal, the same קרבן, korban, whether it's an אשם ודאי asham
vadai or an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So why should I make
you give an אשם תלוי asham talui and then a week later
you'll have to give an אשם ודאי? asham vadai? Just now give
one אשם asham and stipulate. So you'll save yourself having to do
a second one if it turns out you're חייב. chayav. So אמר
לו רבי עקיבא, amar lo Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said
back to him, נראין דבריו במעילה מועטת. nir'in devarav bime'ilah mu'etes. I
can, I would agree that that's a good idea if the amount
of your מעילה me'ilah is very minor, maybe you stole a dollar,
right, or something, a פרוטה, prutah, whatever, then fine, you might as
well do it. הרי, harei, but what if שיבא לספק מעילה במאה
מנה? sheyavo lesafek me'ilah beme'ah maneh?
Let's say you might have misused or stolen from הקדש hekdesh a
thousand dollars. So you're going to tell me pay, right, in order
for the אשם ודאי asham vadai to work you have to return
the money. So you're trying to save this guy buying an extra
animal, but you're forcing him to pay all the money up front,
he may never have to pay the money. לא יפה לו שיביא
אשם בשני סלעים, lo yafeh lo sheyavi asham bishnei sela'im,
isn't it better for him to now bring the אשם ספק asham
safek and maybe he'll never pay the other money because it'll never
turn out that he knows he stole, ולא יביא ספק מעילה במאה
מנה, velo yavi safek me'ilah beme'ah maneh,
and then he wouldn't have to right now, you're suggesting pay the
full money and only bring one אשם. asham. That's fine if it
saves me money, but paying the full money really might cost me
an enormous amount of money. So מודה רבי עקיבא לרבי טרפון, modeh
Rabbi Akiva leRabbi Tarfon, so he would agree to רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon במעילה מועטת, bime'ilah mu'etes, if it was a small amount. This
is all just pragmatic advice, right? It's funny that they're even saying
it, but from there you actually do learn הלכה halachah principles. Number
one, that you can stipulate. Number two, what we'll see in the
גמרא gemara is what you learn. How can you bring an אשם
ודאי asham vadai and say, if it turns out I sinned, this
is my אשם? asham? Don't we, isn't what's necessary to bring a
חטאת, chatat, as we've been talking about, to know that you've sinned?
You can't, if you don't know you sinned, you can't say, "Okay,
if it turns out I sinned, this is my חטאת chatat and
if not, I don't know, it's a נדבה nedavah or whatever." You
can't do that. You have to know you sinned. So one of
the things we learn from this strategy is that actually when it
comes to an אשם, asham, you could bring it על תנאי al
tnai even if you don't yet know you sinned, even an אשם
ודאי. asham vadai. So we'll see, there's a פסוק pasuk by a
חטאת, chatat, right? Right. So we will see that in the גמרא
Gemara you do learn something practical out of this. But the disagreement,
right, is only a question of like what would be a good
strategy. And here Rabbi Akiva is saying it's not a good strategy
to hang up a lot of money right now. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא's Gemara going to focus
on this question about whether you bring an אשם ודאי, asham vadai,
an אשם תלוי asham talui for something you would otherwise bring an
אשם ודאי. asham vadai. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: ואם נפש. V'im nefesh.
So this is the פסוק pasuk where it speaks about an אשם
תלוי: asham talui: ואם נפש כי תחטא ועשתה אחת מכל מצות ה'
אשר לא תעשינה ולא ידע ואשם. V'im nefesh ki techeta v'asatah achat
mikol mitzvot Hashem asher lo teaseinah v'lo yada v'ashem. Right. Right. Or
is that, or is that the one for the, for the חטאת?
chatat? This is, this is, see it says the, the emphasis said
that it's not known to him. Hold on. ואם נפש כי תחטא
ועשתה אחת מכל מצות ה' אשר לא תעשינה ולא ידע ואשם ונשא
עונו. V'im nefesh ki techeta v'asatah achat mikol mitzvot Hashem asher lo
teaseinah v'lo yada v'ashem v'nasa avono. So
that is about the אשם תלוי. asham talui. You're not sure if
you sinned. Now, the פרשה parsha right before that is אשם מעילות.
asham meilot. נפש כי תמעול מעל. Nefesh ki timol maal.
And then it says and you bring an אשם. asham. So first
it says אשם מעילות, asham meilot, then it says that if a
soul doesn't know, you bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So אשם
תלוי asham talui is right after אשם מעילות. asham meilot. So maybe
Rabbi Akiva just learns from the juxtaposition. Let's take a look. ואם
נפש לחייב על ספק מעילות אשם תלוי. V'im nefesh l'chayev al safek
meilot asham talui.
That it's juxtaposed to tell you even if, even when you don't
know if you did מעילה meilah you bring an אשם תלוי. asham
talui. דברי רבי עקיבא, Divrei Rabbi Akiva, that's what Rabbi Akiva says.
וחכמים פוטרין, V'chachamim potrin, the חכמים Chachamim exempt. So the גמרא Gemara
says: לימא בהא קמיפלגי? Leima beha kamiflagi? Maybe this is the debate.
רבי עקיבא סבר למדים עליון מתחתון. Rabbi Akiva savar lamedim elyon mitachton.
We learn, we apply, we learn the top learns from the bottom.
So the first paragraph of אשם, asham. of אשם מעילות asham meilot
learns from the second of אשם תלוי. asham talui. ורבנן סברי אין
למדים עליון מתחתון. V'rabbanan savri ein lamedim elyon mitachton. No,
you don't learn from the juxtaposition. אמר רב פפא דכולי עלמא למדים
עליון מתחתון. Amar Rav Papa d'chulei alma lamedim elyon mitachton. No, we
have to say everybody says you learn from the juxtaposition, certainly by
קרבנות. korbanot. Why? דאם כן צפון בבן בקר לא משכחת לה. D'im
ken tzafon b'ven bakar lo meshkachat lah. Or really, it could mean
like דאי לאו כן. d'ee lav ken. Because if you didn't say
that, you would never know that you have to שחט shacht cattle
in the north. When the תורה Torah says by your עולה, olah,
אם עלה קרבנו מן הבקר, im olah korbano min habakar, and then
it tells you how to bring a cattle עולה, olah, it never
says שחט shacht it in the north. Then when it says ואם
מן הצאן קרבנו, v'im min hatzon korbano, then it says you שחט
shacht it in the north. And the only way you know that
you שחט shacht cattle of an עולה olah in the north is
from the juxtaposition that you learn the second, first פרשה parsha from
the second. So everybody agrees that from, you can learn the, that
you learn the top, the first one from the second. That's a
general principle. So לא משכחת לה. lo meshkachat lah. אלא הכא היינו
טעמא דרבנן דפטרי. Ela hacha hainu taama d'rabbanan d'patrei. So why do
the רבנן Rabbanan say you're exempt if the, if it says אשם
asham מעילות and then אשם תלוי? asham talui? דגמירי מצות מצות מחטאת
מחטאת. D'gemiri mitzvot mitzvot m'chatat m'chatat. מצות מצות מחטאת. Mitzvot mitzvot m'chatat.
Okay. מה להלן דבר שחייבין על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת. Mah
lehalan davar shechayavin al zedono kares v'al shigagato chatat.
Because we have a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. Here it says אחת
מכל מצות ה' ולא נודע וידע ומה שזה לא יהיה ואשם ונשא
עונו. achat mikol mitzvot Hashem v'lo noda v'yada u'mah shezeh lo yihiyeh
v'ashem v'nasa avono. ואשם ונשא עונו. V'ashem v'nasa avono. And by a
חטאת chatat it says אחת מכל מצות ה' אלהיך אשר לא
תעשינה ואשם. achat mikol mitzvot Hashem Elokecha asher lo teaseinah v'ashem.
So it's the same phrase of אחת מכל מצות. achat mikol mitzvot.
It says מצות מצות. mitzvot mitzvot. So we apply אשם תלוי asham
talui is dependent on חטאת. chatat. Okay. מה להלן דבר שחייבין על
זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת. Mah lehalan davar shechayavin al zedono kares
v'al shigagato chatat. The same way over there, it's something that you
bring a חטאת chatat for when it's בשוגג b'shogeg and כרת kares
if it's willful. אף כל שחייבין על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת
Af kol shechayavin al zedono kares v'al shigagato chatat ועל ספקו אשם
תלוי. v'al sefeko asham talui.
Okay, the ספק safek and שגגות shigagot are reversed.
Anyway,
here too, only something that you would get כרת kares if it
was willful, חטאת chatat if you definitely had did it wrong בשוגג.
b'shogeg. Only that would you bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. And
here, you don't get that in either way. יצא לאפוקי מעילה. Yatza
l'afokei meilah. מעילה Meilah is not like this in two ways. דאין
חייבין על זדונו כרת. D'ein chayavin al zedono kares. Number one is,
well first clearly you don't get a חטאת chatat for מעילה meilah
even if you did it definitely, you bring a, you bring an
אשם. asham And number two is, you don't get כרת kares if
you did it willfully. דתניא המזיד במעילה, D'tanya hameizid b'meilah, if you
willfully did מעילה, meilah, רבי אומר במיתה. Rabbi omer b'mitah. מיתה בידי
שמים, Mitah bidei shamayim, not in the court. Heavenly death, which is
different than כרת. kares. וחכמים אומרים באזהרה. V'chachamim omrim b'azharah. It's a
negative prohibition, but nobody says you get כרת kares for מעילה. meilah.
So מעילה meilah is not, is not a normal case of an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. Normal אשם תלוי asham talui is something that
otherwise would be
חטאת chatat or כרת. kares. And this otherwise would
be אשם asham, fat and blood and sexual sins, the normal way
for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to refer to a standard sin חטאת
Chatas *Chatas* is חטאת chatas? חלב cheilev *Chatas Chelev*. Okay, maybe because
maybe because food sins are more common although חלב *Chelev* is not
a very common sin, but anyway רש"י *Rashi* also says that it's
right near the פרשה *Parsha* of חלב *Chelev*. Anyway, that's the standard
way of referring to a sin חטאת chatas. *Chatas* as חטאת chatas
חלב *Chatas Chelev*. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* says, when
do we learn from that to apply to the principle of אשם
תלוי asham taluy *Asham Taloy*? להכי הוא דאתי *Lehachi hu de'asi* for
the following purpose: מה להלן בקבועה אף כאן בקבועה *Mah lehalan bikvuah
af kan bikvuah*, that you only bring an אשם תלוי asham taluy
*Asham Taloy* if when you did it ודאי vadai. *vaday*, you would
bring a fixed sin offering, be it חטאת chatas *Chatas* or be
it אשם asham *Asham*. What does that exclude? לאפוקי עולה ויורד דלא
*Le'apukei oleh veyored delo*. Right? Remember there are five cases at the
end of ויקרא *Vayikra* at the פרשת ויקרא *Parshas Vayikra* where you
can bring a sin, five, anyway you bring a sin where the
value, where the amount, where the value differs based on your ability
to afford it. So that type of a thing where it's a
fluctuating cost of a חטאת chatat *Chatas*, you don't bring an אשם
תלוי asham taluy *Asham Taloy*. But something that's fixed cost, be it
an אשם asham *Asham* or be it a חטאת chatat *Chatas*, you
do bring an אשם תלוי asham taluy *Asham Taloy* for. Okay. ורבנן
סברי *Verabbanan savri* and the rabbis say אין גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah
למחצה *Ein gezeirah shavah lemechetza*. I'm sorry רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi
Akiva*, once you make the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah *gezeirah shavah* and
you link it to a חטאת chatat. *Chatas*, you can't choose which
laws to learn out. So once we link אשם תלוי asham taluy
*Asham Taloy* to a חטאת chatat *Chatas*, it's going to be fully
linked and it's only going to be brought for something that otherwise
would be a חטאת chatat *Chatas*, nothing else. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says מכלל דרבי עקיבא סבר יש גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah למחצה
*Michlal deRabbi Akiva savar yesh gezeirah shavah lemechetza*? Do you mean that
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* would hold that you can apply
a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah *gezeirah shavah* halfway? Obviously not. Obviously you
have to apply a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah. *gezeirah shavah* all the
way. So this is a very good argument. Once we link it
to a חטאת *Chatas*, it should be limited to things that you
bring a חטאת *Chatas* for. אלא יורא *Ella yora*, דכולי עלמא אין
גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah למחצה *dekulei alma ein gezeirah shavah lemechetza*. You
don't learn a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah. *gezeirah shavah* halfway. אלא היינו
טעמא דרבי עקיבא *Ella hainu ta'ama deRabbi Akiva*. So now we're flipping
it. Now we agree that principally you learn from a חטאת *Chatas*
and that tells you it has to be fixed, but it also
tells you it has to be חטאת *Chatas*. So where does רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* come off saying that it doesn't? אלא
היינו טעמא דרבי עקיבא דאמר קרא ואם נפש *Ella hainu ta'ama deRabbi
Akiva de'amar kra ve'im nefesh*. It's not just the juxtaposition. There's a
specific letter that teaches us that you bring it for אשם asham
מעילות *Asham Meilos*. ו מוסיף על ענין ראשון vav mosif al inyan
rishon. *Vav mosif al inyan rishon*. The ו vav *vav* adds to
the previous וילמד עליון מתחתון *veyilamed elyon mitachton* and you learn the
top from the bottom. So we're saying like we said before, but
it's not just juxtaposition, it's a special ו vav *vav*. So of
course the regular rule is a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah *gezeirah shavah*
goes the whole way. But here the extra ו vav *vav* is
telling us there's a special case of אשם תלוי asham taluy, *Asham
Taloy* and that's when it comes in a case of אשם asham,
מעילות *Asham Meilos*. By the way, if that would mean that it
would not apply to other אשמות ashamot *ashamos*, right? Let's say you
had a ספק safek *safek* of an אשם asham *Asham* of שפחה
חרופה *shifcha charufa* or something. Right. גזילות *Gezailos* or whatever. So that
would not apply. It's specifically the exception of אשם asham, מעילות *Asham
Meilos*. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: ורבנן סברי
תחתון הוא דגמר מעליון *Verabbanan savri tachton hu degamar me'elyon* לאשם בכסף
שקלים shekalim. *le'asham bechesef shekalim*. I agree to the ו vav *vav*.
It could have just said the rabbis reject the whole learning of
the ו vav *vav*. I agree the ו vav *vav* connects it,
but for the other way, to tell you that an אשם תלוי
asham taluy. *Asham Taloy* you learn from an אשם asham מעילות *Asham
Meilos*. What does it learn out from an אשם מעילות *Asham Meilos*?
By אשם מעילות *Asham Meilos* it says כסף שקלים *kesef shekalim* and
כסף שקלים *kesef shekalim* in the plural. And that's where we learn
out that the minimum cost of an אשם *Asham* is two שקל
*shekel*, is two סלע sela. *sela*. Okay. So therefore that's in אשם
מעילות *Asham Meilos*. So the ו vav *vav* does tell you to
learn out, but not that you bring an אשם תלוי asham taloi
*Asham Taloy* for אשם מעילות *Asham Meilos*, but rather that an אשם
תלוי asham taloi. *Asham Taloy* you learn from מעילות *Meilos* and has
to cost two שקל *shekel*. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva סבר *Rabbi Akiva
savar* רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says אין היקש hekesh, למחצה
*ein hekesh lemechetza*. Sorry guys, what you're saying back to me I'll
say to you. Once you admit that they're linked, they're linked the
full way and therefore if you're going to learn out in one
direction that it has the minimum cost, you gotta learn out in
the other direction that you bring an אשם תלוי asham taloi. *Asham
Taloy* for מעילה me'ilah. *Meilah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מכלל
דרבנן סברי יש היקש למחצה *Michlal deRabbanan savri yesh hekesh lemechetza*? So
now we're sort of reversing it. So that means the rabbis would
say you can learn a היקש *hekesh* halfway? והא קיימא לן דאין
היקש למחצה *Veha kayma lan de'ein hekesh lemechetza*? But we hold you
can't learn a היקש *hekesh* halfway. רש"י *Rashi* by the way has
a whole different גירסא *girsa* of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* because he
says this isn't a problem of אין היקש למחצה *ein hekesh lemechetza*.
But anyway, דכולי עלמא *dekulei alma*. So anyway now we're back to
this. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says if you admit
to the ו vav *vav*, then you gotta admit to me the
whole way that you can bring an אשם תלוי asham taloi, *Asham
Taloy*. So what do the rabbis do with that? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says okay, you're right. דכולי עלמא אין היקש למחצה *Dekulei
alma ein hekesh lemechetza*. You don't do it halfway. So how do
the rabbis get out of the ו vav. *vav*? והכא היינו טעמא
דרבנן *Vehacha hainu ta'ama deRabbanan* דגמרי מצות מצות אפקי מהיקשא *degamri mitzvos
mitzvos afkei mehekesha*. We have two competing דרשות *drashos*. We have the
ו vav *vav* that links them and we've got the מצות מצות
*mitzvos mitzvos*. It says it's dependent on a חטאת *Chatas*. So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says the ו vav *vav* that links
them overrides the limit to a חטאת *Chatas*. And the rabbis say
no, the limit to a חטאת *Chatas* overrides the link. And therefore
the link, it's not, you wouldn't bring it for an אשם *Asham*
and the link only tells you the idea of two שקלים *shekalim*,
but it doesn't work both ways because that's overridden from the גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah*. That's pretty clear. You got the גזירה שוה *gezeirah
shavah* that tells you that אשם *Asham* is linked to חטאת *Chatas*
and you've got the ו vav *vav* that links אשם *Asham* to
אשם מעילות *Asham Meilos*. So the question is which one wins? So
the rabbis say the גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* wins and the only
thing you learn from this link is the minimum price and רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says no, this ו wins and therefore the גזירה
שוה only tells you fixed value but it does not tell you
חטאת like. Look let me see he used the other name but
I'm not sure. Look let me see what he said. Yeah that's
not his name. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so
that's why they say, they say the גזירה שוה overrides. So רבי
עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva now what would רבי עקיבא say? Because the גמרא
Gemara assumes that רבי עקיבא should admit that a גזירה שוה is
more powerful than a, than a היקש, so the גזירה שוה should
override. So here's why רבי עקיבא is going to say it's not.
אשם בכסף שקלים נפקא ליה מזאת תורת האשם. Asham b'kesef shekalim nafka
lei mi-zos toras ha-asham. We know that there's a minimum cost of
an אשם that applies to all אשמות ashamot from the, because it
says this is the law of the אשם, תורה אחת לכל האשמות.
torah achas l'chol ashamot. לאשם דכסף שקלים, L'asham d'kesef shekalim, there's one
law for all אשמות ashamot that there's a minimum cost of two
שקלים. Why is that relevant here? זאת תורת Zos toras just means
same law. So anyway, why is that relevant here? Because now it's
telling you this: the ו that links them isn't needed to tell
you the point of minimum cost. We know that from somewhere else.
So the only purpose of the ו that links them is to
tell you you bring an אשם תלוי asham taloi. for מעילה. me'ilah?
So you've got competing things, you've got a ו here that links
and you've got a גזירה שוה. The רבנן rabbis say גזירה שוה
override, sorry you're not going to bring an אשם for an אשם
תלוי asham taloi. for an אשם מעילה. asham me'ilah. And רבי עקיבא
says no, I'm sorry, the only thing you need the ו here
for is to tell me that הלכה. halacha. You don't need it
to tell me minimum cost. And therefore, since it's only needed to
tell me that הלכה, halacha, it is telling me that you do
bring an אשם ספק, asham safek, an אשם תלוי asham taloi for
a ספק אשם מעילות, safek asham me'ilot, and that overrides what we
learn from the גזירה שוה. Okay, so that's what he says. רבנן,
Rabbanan, and what do the רבנן rabbis say back? Why can't you
learn it out from there? Why do they argue the ו is
needed to tell you that? אף על פי דכתיב זאת תורת האשם,
Af al pi d'ksiv zos toras ha-asham, even though we have that
general, that פסוק pasuk that generalizes it, איצטריך למכתב ואם נפש, itzrich
l'michtav v'im nefesh, ו מוסיף על ענין ראשון ללמד תחתון מן העליון.
vav mosif al inyan rishon l'lamed tachton min ha-elyon. You need the
ו to still teach me that principle of minimum cost. די מזאת
תורת האשם, D'ee mi-zos toras ha-asham, had it just been from that
general statement of זאת תורת האשם, zos toras ha-asham, הוה אמינא hava
amina I would say, כי אמינא תורה אחת לכל האשמות, ki amina
torah achas l'chol ashamot, when would I say one law for all
אשמות ashamot of the minimum cost? הני מילי בשאר אשמות ודאי. Hani
mili b'sha'ar ashamot vadai. That's all אשמות ashamot that are
אשם ודאי. asham vadai. אבל אשם תלוי, Aval asham taluy, but an
אשם that is brought for a doubtful sin,
that's maybe not as weighty. כיון דעל ספק חלב אתי, Keivan d'al
safek cheilev ati, since it's only from a doubtful sin, again notice
חלב as the example, a doubtful sin, אימא לא יהא חומר מודאי,
eima lo yehei chomer mi-vadai, maybe I shouldn't have a higher cost
for the אשם for the doubtful sin than what I would bring
if I definitely sinned. If I definitely sinned, what is the minimum
cost of a חטאת? There basically is no minimum cost of a
חטאת. מה ודאי חטאת בר דנקא, Ma vadai chatas bar danka, if
you bring a, when you bring a חטאת it can even be
the cost of a דנקא, danka, I forget what it is, I
think it's like a sixth of a סלע. So therefore you can
bring a חטאת that costs almost nothing. Where you're going to get
a sheep for that little money, who knows? But the point is
there's no minimum cost. So if there's no minimum cost when you
definitely sinned, I would have assumed that for an אשם תלוי there's
also no minimum cost. אספקא אשם בר דנקא, Asfeka asham bar danka,
I would say that by an אשם תלוי it's the same. So
even though there's a זאת תורת החטאת, zos toras ha-chatas, I need
the אשם, I need the ו to tell me it applies even
to אשם תלוי, because logic would have told me there should be
no minimum cost for אשם תלוי. הכי, Hachi, therefore, כתב רחמנא ואם
נפש, kasav rachmana v'im nefesh, ו מוסיף על ענין ראשון. And that's
why it had the ו. By the way, the גמרא Gemara elsewhere
and the בעלי תשובה, ba'alei teshuvah, not בעלי תשובה, ba'alei teshuvah, the
בעלי מוסר ba'alei mussar speak about the importance of this lesson for
תשובה. teshuvah. That it says that when you know you've definitely done
something wrong, it's easier to do תשובה teshuvah for it. When you
think, eh, maybe I did something wrong, you rationalize, you tell yourself
you didn't, so even if you do תשובה teshuvah it's not so
sincere. So therefore by a ספק safek the תורה Torah demands more
actually in terms of cost than by the ודאי. vadai Anyway, so
now the גמרא goes on.
So you have it here too, even on a ספק מעילה אשם.
safek me'ilah asham. Well, about by ספק מעילה. safek me'ilah. הני ניחא
למאן דדרש זאת תורת האשם. Hani nicha l'man d'darish zos toras ha-asham.
Now we understand where רבי עקיבא says you don't need the ו
to teach me this הלכה halacha because you get it from זאת
תורת האשם. zos toras ha-asham. אלא למאן דלא דרש זאת תורת האשם
מאי למימר? Ella l'man d'lo darish zos toras ha-asham mai l'meimar? There's
an opinion that says we don't learn זאת תורת zos torat to
apply the law across the board. So we're back to the issue.
How can רבי עקיבא tell me the ו teaches you אשם ספק
asham safek for מעילה? Maybe it's just to tell me the הלכה
halacha of the minimum cost. So the גמרא says no, we can
learn minimum cost yet from another place.
יליף בערכך בערכך מאשם מעילה, Yalif b'erkecha b'erkecha me-asham me'ilah, that there's
a גזירה שוה בערכך בערכך gezeirah shavah erkecha erkecha from אשם מעילה
asham me'ilah that tells me the other אשמות ashamote, is also the
same minimum cost. ואשם שפחה חרופה דלא כתיב בערכך, V'asham shifcha charufa
d'lo ksiv b'erkecha, and there's one אשם that it doesn't say בערכך
b'erkecha cost, where do we know there? יפינן באיל איל, Yafinan b'ayil
ayil, there's another גזירה שוה of איל איל ayil ayil ram. So
the basic point is the ו for רבי עקיבא links the two
פרשיות. parshiyot. The
רבנן, an אשם תלוי for a ספק אשם מעילה. safek asham meila.
But again it seems to be not a general principle you bring
it for אשמות, it seems to be a specific exception for אשם
מעילה. asham meila, Let's just finish to the משנה. mishna. Okay, מודה
רבי עקיבא. Modeh Rebbi Akiva. Now here is the whole trick of
he says well bring one and stipulate. And then רבי עקיבא says
yeah but I don't want to pay out all the money right
now if it's a serious payment. So the גמרא says but now
we're going to talk about the language of the stipulation. The stipulation
is if I definitely sinned it'll be an אשם ודאי asham vadai
and if I doubtfully sinned it'll be an אשם תלוי. What do
you mean? You did doubtfully sin and you are חייב chayav in
אשם תלוי. So גמרא says ואם ספק v'im safek if I doubtfully
sinned מאי קאמר mai ka'amar what are you saying? You did doubtfully.
אמר רב הונא הכי תני, Amar Rav Huna hachi tani, תני אם
בספקו עומד לעולם יהא אשם תלוי. tani im b'sfeko omed l'olam yehei
asham taloi. Say like this: if it turns out that I eventually
find out sometime in the future that I definitely sinned and I'll
be חייב chayav an אשם ודאי asham vadai that this be the
אשם ודאי. asham vadai. If it turns out that I never in
my life discover whether I've sinned or not, so then I'm חייב
chayav an אשם תלוי, not an אשם ודאי, asham vadai, let this
be the אשם תלוי. Okay, so if it becomes an אשם, if
it becomes a ודאי let this be my אשם ודאי, asham vadai,
if it remains a ספק safek forever let this be an אשם
תלוי. שם מין שהביא על הודע מביא על לא הודע. Shem min
shehevi al hoda mevi al lo hoda. So the one you bring
because it's the same animal you bring whether it's an אשם תלוי
or אשם ודאי. asham vadai. So גמרא says סוף סוף sof sof
כי משתדע ליה ki mishtada lei what do I care? Even if
you wind up finding out a year later or ten years or
even a day later, בעית לאתויי אשם ודאי bayat l'atuyei asham vadai
you're still obligated in your אשם ודאי asham vadai because you don't
bring your right you don't bring your חטאת ודאי chatat vadai until
you know for sure. Right? Why do you ever have to do
the whole thing? Why not just always bring if you have a
ספק bring a חטאת and stipulate? וההלכה היא V'hahalachah hi is that
you do not bring a חטאת unless you have או הודע לו
o hoda lo you become definitely aware. So how can you bring
it if you're not yet aware? When you become aware then you'll
be obligated, not now. So the גמרא says אמר
רבא amar Rava מדברי שניהם נלמד midivrei shneihem nilmad from both רבי
עקיבא and רבי טרפון Rebbi Tarfon because they agree in principle. So
from both of them we can learn אשם ודאי לא בעי ידיעה
בתחילה. asham vadai lo bei yediya batchila. That an אשם ודאי asham
vadai does not require שיהא לכתחילה בתחילה. sheyehei l'chatchila batchila. An אשם
ודאי asham vadai you do not have to be aware before you
bring the קרבן. korban. And in this way an אשם ודאי asham
vadai is different from an אשם ספק. asham safek. Okay, from I
mean from a חטאת. By a חטאת we've been emphasizing או הודע
אליו חטאתו, o hoda eilav chatato, so חטאת there is no obligation
until you actually know. By an אשם ודאי asham vadai you can
actually bring it now and if it turns out later you become
aware. It doesn't mean it sounds like if I never become aware
in my life then this cannot have been even if God knows
this wouldn't have been an אשם ודאי. asham vadai. It's not objectively
I did it even if I'm not aware. The awareness is important
but the awareness can come doesn't have to be בתחילה. batchila. The
awareness can come later. If I became aware ten years later that
is enough to say that the אשם I brought earlier is an
אשם ודאי. asham vadai. Okay, you got it? So I don't have
to be aware I can't bring it if I'm not aware just
because God knows it still won't be an אשם ודאי. asham vadai.
It's only an אשם ודאי asham vadai if I become aware but
that requirement can come after can be satisfied after the קרבן korban
is brought retroactively. So therefore this can be this can be an
אשם תלוי אשם ודאי asham taloi asham vadai depending on what happens
later whether I do find out or don't find out and then
the only question is is it a good strategy based on whether
I have to pay up the money now.